Guide to the City Club of New York Records 1890-1978 MS 116
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Records and Correspondence Files, 1890s-1957; 4.75 Linear feet
  - Subseries II.G. Miscellaneous, 1943-1957; 0.25 Linear feet
    - To be Filed, 1953-1954 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
      Includes: correspondence, requests for information, minutes (1953-1954), notice of office move, and minutes regarding move and deposit of City Club materials to New-York Historical Society.
    - Miscellaneous - City Club, 1953-1957 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
      Includes Board of Trustees minutes and materials, 1955 member list, remarks by Benjamin J. Buttenweiser, Legislation Committee materials, release regarding Mayor Wagner's performance, Nominating Committee materials, and financials.
    - Miscellaneous Reports, clippings, etc., 1943-1951 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
      Includes: newspaper clippings, reports, civil program pamphlets, memorandums, and City Club Bulletins.
    - Matters to be Taken care of - E. H., 1943 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
      Includes: Notes for Miss Harft, correspondence, membership roster, list of addresses, City Club code of accounts, and Board of Trustee minutes.
    - Rubber Stamps, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
      Four rubber stamps: Trustee Copy for your information only, Past Due - Please Remit, Trustees, Property of City Club.
- Series III. Scrapbooks, 1911-1953; 3.5 Linear feet
  The series contains four scrapbooks which span from 1912-1953. The first three of the scrapbooks contain a mixture of items including news clippings, minutes, reports, and ephemera from 1912-1941. The fourth scrapbook contains primarily news clippings that reference City Club or Club members. Note- the scrapbooks are fragile as the binding has separated from the pages, and the pages have become brittle.
  The four scrapbooks are in chronological order of the contents and are in two record cartons and one flat archival storage box.
  - Scrapbook, 1911-1919 (Offsite-box 8)
    Includes materials from 1911 up through 1919 including invitations to concerts, operas, dinners, benefits, and materials from the 25th Anniversary Dinner of the Club. Cards are included from lectures and meetings which include the topics and titles, and notices of outings, programs, and menus. There is the document of incorporation for Century Opera Company, of which City Club members aided in the foundation of, pledge cards, letters to legislators, election materials, materials in opposition to the subway expansion (1912-1913), Dental Hygiene for Public Schools report, Resolution regarding fire protection, Military State Census of 1917, and other financial sheets, membership materials, and reports.
  - Scrapbook, 1920-1935 (Offsite-box 8)
    Includes City Club Bulletins, invitations to events including Armistice Night Dinner, Treasurer's Reports, business directory of members, member handbook, City Club Results pamphlet, annual reports, House Income and Expenses, election materials, advertisement for club amenities, reports, an "About City Club" booklet, and other ephemera.
  - Scrapbook, 1935-1941 (Offsite-box 9)
    Includes Club Luncheon invitations and Luncheon club notices, voting recommendations, Club election materials, committee reports, City Club Bulletins, outline of civic plan (1940-1941), Club services memo, City Club advertisement materials, floor plan of City Club building, and other ephemera.
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1953 (Offsite-box 12)
    Includes news clippings that discuss City Club and its civic efforts, and letters to members. Topics include: voting recommendations, legislation, actions towards members of the Communist Party, notice of awards given, City Club election results, City Club 50th Anniversary, obituaries, luncheons, the East Side re-zoning plan, health insurance, New York City Transit report, Michael Quill and the transit strike, re-zoning of the U.N. site, police reporting, civil defense, investigation of former Mayor O'Dwyer, and waterfront crime.
- Series IV. Publications, 1892-1950, 1959-1978; 3.42 Linear feet
  The materials in this series are the publications, releases, and reports put out by City Club. These materials are loose pamphlets and bound volumes. The Year Books of City Club contain member rosters, photographs of the Club House, the by-laws, constitution, and purpose of the club, and one contains annual reports. The Miscellaneous Publications volumes contain committee reports, addresses given to the club, reports on various civic matters including legislation, elections, transportation, the health department, police, and other publications. Other publications included in the series are numerous copies of pamphlet publications put out by City Club and its committees, and their publications to members, City Club Bulletin, which later became City Club Comments.
  The materials in this series are arranged within boxes and as numbered volumes by format within chronological order. Generally yearbooks and reports are presented first, followed by newsletters and bulletins. Volumes that were fragile were boxed and stable volumes are shelved individually. Standalone pamphlets are ordered by year of publication within folders, ending with two reports from the 1970s. There is some degree of overlap across the formats (e.g., some pamphlets can be found both standalone in folders and in bound volumes).
  - Year Books (2 copies), 1892-1900 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9-10)
    Includes articles of incorporation, constitution, by-laws, house rules, purpose of club, officers, committees, members. One copy is incomplete.
  - Year Books, 1901-1905 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
    Includes constitution, by-laws, committees, members, deaths, and house rules.
  - Year Books, 1906-1910 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    Includes photographs of Club House, constitution, by-laws, committees, members, deaths, articles of incorporation and house rules.
  - Year Books and Annual Reports, 1911-1916 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    Includes photographs of Club House, annual reports of the Board of Trustees including committee updates and finances, constitution, by-laws, house rules, rosters, and membership.
  - Annual Reports- Council, Secretary, Trustees, 1894-1904 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    Includes bound copies of annual reports given at City Club annual meetings.
  - The City Club of New York By-laws (3 copies), 1917 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
    Includes 3 copies of City Club's Constitution, By-laws, House rules, Members, Officers, Trustees, and Annual Report. The volumes also include photographs of the Club House.
  - Miscellaneous Bound Publications (2 copies), 1892-1899 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-2)
    Includes two copies of publications book, one incomplete. Topics include: the Charter of Greater New York, Legislation, Public Works, Ramapo Water Scheme and Water Supply reports.
  - Miscellaneous Bound Publications (2 copies), 1900-1902 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3-4)
    Includes two copies of publication book, one is incomplete. Topics include the New York Charter, Ten Months of Tammany, Water Supply publications and legislation, report "What Parents Should Know" on women forced into "disorderly houses" and prostitution and the charges against Asa Bird Gardiner, New York District Attorney.
  - City Club's Publications, 1903 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
    Includes reports on the Police Department, Department of Water Supply, Gas and Electricity, Department of Bridges, Health Department, Candidates for Election to Municipal Office, and Transit. Duplicates of reports available in Miscellaneous Bound Publications for 1903 below.
  - Miscellaneous Bound Publications (2 copies), 1903-1905 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 5-6)
    Includes two copies of the volume. Topics include the Health Department and city hospitals, elections, Police affairs and trials, the Raines Law Hotel and prostitution, and accompanying photographs of hospitals, watersheds, bridges, and proposed changes.
  - Miscellaneous Bound Publications (2 copies), 1905-1910 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 7-8)
    Includes two copies of the volume. Materials include reports on Transit, Legislation, Schools, an obituary booklet, Annual Reports, and a booklet on proposed preservation of City Hall Park from becoming the site of the new Court House.
  - Miscellaneous Bound Publications (2 copies), 1911-1916 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9-10)
    Includes two copies of the volume. Materials include reports on the water supply, annual reports, employment, and legislation reports. Includes addresses from a series of dinners honoring foreign ambassadors Hon. James Bryce, British Ambassador, Count Johann H. Von Bernstorff, German Ambassador, and Address by Hon. J. Hampden Dougherty on the proposed New York Charter.
  - Miscellaneous Bound Publications (2 copies), 1917-1930 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11-12)
    Includes two copies of the volume. Materials are bound copies of loose pamphlets which include report and address on the New York City Charter, City Club updates and activities, reports on City planning and growth, transit, electricity, the courts, and the proposed Hofstadter bill that would require elected officials to waive immunity in investigations.
  - Miscellaneous Publications Pamphlets (4 folders), 1908-1929 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-4)
    Loose pamphlets, duplicates of reports in bound Miscellaneous Publications volumes.
  - Miscellaneous Publications Pamphlets, 1930-1932 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 5)
    Includes copies of "Blue Laws and Fool Laws", "Subway Overcrowding", "The Untermyer Plan for Subway Unification", and "The Problem of Applying the City Manager Plan to New York".
  - Miscellaneous Publications Pamphlets, 1932-1937 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 6)
    Includes copies of "An Improved Procedure for Investigating Municipal Affairs", "Selection of Judges", "Modernize the Legislature!", and "Report on Proposed Legislation Relating to Labor Unions".
  - Miscellaneous Publications Pamphlets, 1938 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 7)
    Includes copies of the reports "The Next Step in Community Planning", "Solving the Mortgage Moratorium Problem", "Apportionment", "A Bill Drafting Bureau for the City Council", and "Property Assessment Review".
  - Miscellaneous Publications Pamphlets, 1938-1939 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 8)
    Includes copies of reports "Home Rule", "City Residence and the Right to Vote", "New York City's Pension Problem", and "A Deposit System for Independent Nominations".
  - Miscellaneous Publications Pamphlets, 1940-1950 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 9)
    Includes copies of reports "Regulation of Neon Signs", "Reform the Foreclosure Practice", "The Adolescent Boy and The Detention Prison", "Removal of Judges", and "First Report of the Special Committee on Civil Defense".
  - Report on Health and Hospitals, 1975 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 10)
  - Public Hearing on the Establishment of a Health Services Agency for New York City, 1975 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 10)
  - Bound Bulletins and Miscellaneous Leaflets, 1906-1916 (Offsite-box CC-16, Volume 64)
    Includes materials on the New York Charter and Constitution, legislation, public health, Century Opera Company, employment, Club finances, transit, the police department, and taxation. One of two identical volumes.
  - Bound Bulletins and Miscellaneous Leaflets, 1906-1916 (Offsite-box CC-16, Volume 65)
    Includes materials on the New York Charter and Constitution, legislation, public health, Century Opera Company, employment, Club finances, transit, the police department, and taxation. Second of two identical volumes.
  - Bound Bulletins and Miscellaneous Leaflets, 1916-1922 (Offsite-box CC-16, Volume 66)
    Includes materials on New York Constitutional Amendments, annual reports, treasurer's reports, building regulations, and program from Century Opera Company All Star Benefit Performance honoring the Metropolitan Ambulance Unit before their departure for France with photographs of the Unit. One of two duplicate volumes, this volume includes news clipping of City Club's brief to the Judiciary Article Constitutional Convention.
  - Bound Bulletins and Miscellaneous Leaflets, 1916-1922 (Offsite-box CC-16, Volume 67)
    Includes materials on New York Constitutional Amendments, annual reports, treasurer's reports, building regulations, and program from Century Opera Company All Star Benefit Performance honoring the Metropolitan Ambulance Unit before their departure for France with photographs of the Unit. Second of two duplicate volumes.
  - Bound Bulletins and Miscellaneous Leaflets, 1922-1930 (Offsite-box CC-16, Offsite-box 68)
    Includes treasurer's reports and booklet on City Club's history by Henry Curran. One of two identical volumes.
  - Bound Bulletins and Miscellaneous Leaflets, 1922-1930 (Offsite-box CC-16, Volume 69)
    Includes treasurer's reports and booklet on City Club's history by Henry Curran. Second of two identical volumes.
  - City Club Comments (2 folders), 1959-1978 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20-21)
    Comments include thoughts, suggestions, and criticisms on various topics including politics, legislation, voting suggestions, transit, city housing, police, and include new members, event schedules, Club finances, and a list of monthly issues from 1959 to 1974.